today I'm going to talk about one of the
touchy subjects in the modern world and
that is the topic of gender and to help
us with this very touchy subject I think
one of the best writers about gender is
Yvonne Ilic who wrote a book called
gender in the 1980s and very soon after
writing this book he he disappeared
completely he he left the public life
and one of the reasons for that is that
it was basically crucified for his
claims by the feminist establishment and
his claims were that gender mattered
that gender was important and he pointed
out that in the nineteen century if
you'd go to a farm you'd see that all
the tools that were female were
completely designed in a different way
than the tools that were male in other
words gender in the in the history until
the 20th century was so extremely
polarized that it would be inconceivable
to think of the tasks of men and women
to be in any sense belonging to the same
sphere so it's no wonder that he was you
know so criticized
I mean we've greeted this breakdown of
categories of genders has beingness
extraordinary emancipatory movement and
I don't want to take away from that but
I think we were seeing today a kind of
extreme collapse of categories which
makes us want to go back and explore and
rediscover what what gender is precisely
I would
listening to this guy named Jonathan
pazzo and he was talking about how in
sports teams when you have the collapse
of the categories of male and female in
sports teams the result is that the men
dominate and that's because in most
physical sports you know men are
physically more stronger yeah physically
stronger and therefore if you collapse
the boundary between male and female
women get oppressed by their not having
their own category so if you know women
compete against each other and work with
each other then you have female
excellence rising to the top and we can
appreciate that and if similarily if the
men you know compete and work with each
other you can have male excellence rise
to the top and we can appreciate that
but in this very well-meaning desire to
collapse all all categories you collapse
all the categories and the women end up
being much more oppressed and bye-bye
the so-called patriarchy then they were
before and I think this was even at the
next point it's this point is that in
the industrial world when there's this
sort of non category this unisex
category it actually becomes a new form
of oppression for women so
complementarity means that the male and
female principle complement each other
they're not at the in this sort of
eternal conflict which we see really
today yeah so that's all very nice and
good you might say but what do we do and
isn't all the games we've made for women
important and of course I mean
absolutely I mean you'd have to be a bit
of a
reactionary or you'd have to be a
somewhat malevolent person not not I
don't think want the best for all women
but again you've had this situation in
Sweden where the the the legal let's say
categories of male and female genders
collapsed and you had a had even more
extreme polarities result that's because
when you collapse the social categories
of male and female
the deeper biological you know and
historical categories subconscious
categories are man male and female
remain and might even get to get get
stronger
why do we might even become more
polarized so difference and what argue
matters difference is important
distinction is important to differences
between us are important men and women
are the same and different how are they
the same I'm not a social scientist but
I think the research is pretty clear and
then in this in this way that men and
women are just as smart as each other
and if you look on the extreme
distributions you see that there's a lot
more male Psychopaths you know and a lot
more male geniuses as well unfortunately
nobody likes this but seems to be the
case and so what do we do okay so
obviously nobody is arguing that we well
some people are but a reasonable person
would not argue that we go into this
kind of regressive we go back into
history and where men were really men
and women were really men also no just
kidding
where the men were men and women were
women and you know they lived in this
sort of you know they had these fixed
roles no one really wants that I studied
I studied Zen and there was this in
Maxim and it goes something like this
first there are mountains and rivers
then there are no mountains and rivers
then there are mountains and rivers
again so mountains and rivers are the
male and the female principle right
quite obviously that's one way to look
at this formulation you could look at
that in terms of male and female sex but
you could also look at it in terms of
male and female tendencies or the
receiving right which is the river the
river receives the earth the water
receives the earth and the mountain the
mountain rises up out of the earth so
they're very obvious male and female
symbolism there so yes in the beginning
of history men were men women were women
and they both had very particular roles
and then the postmodern age came along
the modern and the postmodern age and
the Industrial Age and no men were not
men anymore and women were not women
anymore in other words these categories
seemed insufficient and it seemed that
women and men both both wanted to cross
over into the realm of the other which
is a very interesting process if we
could think of the male and the female
principle you know beyond just merely
the biological male and the biological
female the synthesis and antithesis the
two different cosmic forces that are
rubbing off each other and having this
creative effect see because if there's
no polarity there's no spark there's no
child there's no creativity so there has
to be polarity on the other hand if
polarity gets too stuffy and uptight and
traditional the weight then the inertia
gets such that the polarities collapse
and that's where we're at right now
you know largely in the culture is that
the polarities have collapsed on the
social level but on an unconscious or
collective unconscious level or on a
biological level or on all these
subterranean levels you know of our who
we are
there's there's still this male and
female dance going on and it's a it's
not a pretty dance particularly it's
this can be quite almost violent but
nevertheless is still going on there has
to be polarities so I believe in an
integral age right so you have this is
Ken Wilbur's formulation I and others
you have the the modern age which is
basically unisex right men anyway I've
been doing the same job jobs then you
have the postmodern age where you have
almost a reversal you know of gender
where men are meant to become very
sensitive and maternal and you know
caregiving and all that and women are
meant to be aggressive and assertive and
and compete in the male world and often
out-compete them in and and all that and
now we have you know and will will would
say the next stage is the integral stage
and obviously the integral stage would
be when these repo Lera T's reassert
themselves after after they've collapsed
and they've learned the lesson of the
Apocalypse you could say because the
collapse of all categories is like a
it's kind of an apocalypse it has its it
has its great interest in benefits and
fertile chaos
I'm not as critical as the postmodern
world this is perhaps Jordan Peterson is
or or others but but they're they're
absolutely correct to point out that the
extreme dangers of a total apps collapse
of category and the necessity for
categories like gender to reassert
themselves in fact they do reassert
themselves this is Jordan Peterson's
example in Sweden there's more female
nurses and male engineers than ever
before and that's as a result of the
collapse of categories cuz you know
nature is not this thing that we just
want to follow right well there also has
to be a transcendental element to
experience you know nature and culture
are always again it's it's you know it's
it's the symbolism of male and female
even in and you know non-traditional
couples are gay couples you know you see
that there's there's still there's still
a polarity going on there's still a
dynamic there's still a receiver and a
giver there's still this penetrating
masculinity and this feminine
receptivity there's also a fierce
feminine archetype which tends to be
feared and not really represented in the
culture except maybe in popular culture
where it comes comes through but we
don't want to have this you know I think
I think feminists and don't don't want
to have this nice female archetype you
know because the female archetype can be
ferocious as well just try to approach a
pregnant tiger you will have a taste of
the ferociousness of the female
archetype
so the beauty of these archetypes is
that they have two sides they're not
monological so um I wanted to talk about
even illness because I think he
apparently he kind of brought this term
gender into the discussion and then
disappeared and then this term was taken
over by the the post modernists so
gender is always about oppression right
okay which which it can be but that's
only one dimension of the story okay
the other dimension of the story the
important dimension of the story is is
its complementarity that the male and
female principles you know compliment
each other so the mountain and the river
are not two separate things I was
listening to a Jewish mystic speak and
he said that in Jewish tradition the
Holy Spirit is considered too feminine
and it says that in one of these you
know traditional texts like the Zohar it
says if it's the woman principle it's
not present then the Holy thing then God
is not present or the Holy Spirit is not
present and so we don't want to go back
to polarity in that sense of the two
sexes being separate we want to go back
to polarity in the sense of the two
sexes being interdependent and
interpenetrating and and creative and
renew that creative spark of polarity
which gets lost when all categories are
flattened out there's no interest in
being asexual or saying that distinction
and polarity and difference and these
traditional categories are not arbitrary
they're not socially constructed
were born into these categories and then
we lose them and then they become
valuable again I think that in my 20s I
didn't give a about masculinity
what it meant you know I was just
interested in being a person and I was
very close to women and and I had this
extreme love of women and I wanted to be
a woman almost I grew my hair long you
know there's this identification with
the female sex and and then later on I I
realized that I that I was missing
something that that that the masculine
force is key is is important and I
needed to read reintegrate that or I
need to reintegrate that being a sort of
postmodern feminist guy I need to learn
to become highly you know assertive and
cutting in fierce in a masculine way not
just kind and open and compassionate all
those valuable stereotypical feminine
characteristics so the cutting edge
right as my friend David fuller says the
cutting edge really is is is the
rediscovery of polarity in this time you
know something different in the 60s the
sixties it was the rediscovery of
freedom from polarity now is the time
for reintegration of polarity that's at
least that's what it seems like to me
thank you for listening